You'll need to find the Book of Leaves.
你要找到~之
You are closer every day.
你每天都在接近
Lorenzo makes an embassy to the Duke of Urbino.
洛佐正在比Z公爵
Brilliant!
漂亮!
He seeks to create a new military alliance.
他希望c他建立新的事盟
It's too long since I led my men into combat.
我已很久]有人⒓舆^痿Y了
Our proposal is timely indeed.
看 我的求非常mr
End the House of Medici.
o我值裘赖谄婕易
Before I end you.
不然我就值裟
Those caught roaming the streets after curfew
l宵禁後在街上f逛 我就把他的名字
get put in my little book.
到宰由
Anyone who breaks curfew, for the slightest reason, will be put down here.
o什N理由 `反宵禁的人都被下
Including the true spy whom you believe framed Becchi.
包括那真正的g 那_陷奇的人
You've seen what happens when people question
岩山掏⒂是什N下
the plans of the Vatican, haven't you?
你^了吧?
Giuliano, he'd make a fine husband for Camilla.
朱利Z 可以成榭米拉的好丈夫...
The key.
匙
It's waiting in Rome.
在_R
Your mother, she's alive.
你母H活著
He's alone.
只有他自己
For the first time in days.
@是滋淼牡谝淮
See for yourself, Zo.
你自己看看 _
Careful.
小心
The lenses are delicately balanced.
R片{好
Why is he here while the rest of the city's busy with the carnival?
全城都在^狂g 他到@碜鍪颤N?
What's the name on that headstone?
那墓碑上刻的什N名字?
I can't make it out.
我看不清
The lenses can be adjusted.
R片可以再{
Here.
o我
Celia Lysimachus.
西莉・利西R科斯
That's a Jewish surname.
@是q太姓氏
Explains why she's buried in a pauper's graveyard.
y怪被埋在民墓Y
Who is she?
她是l?
And what is she to Riario?
她和瑞阿里W什NPS?
Maybe only gets stiff for the stiff.
大概是臭味相投吧
You might be right.
有可能
He's on the move.
他要走了
Maestro, look, we've been following Riario for days.
大 我已跟瑞阿里W好滋炝
- If he sees us...  - He won't.
- f一被他lF...  - 不的
Leo, while I'm not about to piss down my leg, I have to side with Nico.
R昂 m然我不被瑞阿里W得尿子 我是同意尼科的看法
I know the Abyssinian claimed the other key's here but look around.
我知道那阿比西尼人f那匙的另一半在@Y 但是你看啊
Rome's been growing for thousands of years.
_R有浊年的v史
An object looking for a place to hide couldn't have chosen a better home.
要藏一|西 ]有比@Y更y被人lF的地方了
Indeed. And that's why we're going to liberate it,
]e 所以我才要把它哪
from the one place Riario would expect it to be safe.
瑞阿里W自以榘踩的地方拿走
The Vatican's Secret Archives.
梵蒂的秘室
Remember, man, that thou art dust and unto dust thou shalt return.
住 你生於m土亦湮於m土
Turn away from sin, Clarice.
hx罪孽 克拉斯
And be faithful to the Gospel.
忠\於福音
I try, brother.
我的 哥哥
As Matthew urges, I pray for those who persecute me.
如R太教 我槠群ξ业娜似矶\
Remember, man, that thou art dust and unto dust thou shalt return.
住 你生於m土亦湮於m土
I've got the guard rotations for the south entrance.
我拿到了南城T的守lQ班D
Tight as a nun on Good Friday.
巡查o得像耶d受y日的尼姑一
We've examined every entrance, window,
我查了每座城T 窗
tunnel, hole in the bloody wall.
地道 城的破洞
Getting in uncaught is impossible.
lF根本不可能混M去
You do realize "impossible" is just a word that makes me try even harder.
"不可能"@~只我更想L
Maestro, sentries patrol every possible entrance.
大 每城T都有哨兵巡
In fact, here come two now.
其 那就砹
Don't worry, my friends.
e心 朋友
As long as they think you're Jews here in the ghetto,
只要他以槟是q太民
you have nothing to fear.
你就不用心
As Jews we are beneath notice.
]人在意q太人
You see, they pay no attention because you wear the yellow.
看啊 你穿著S色衣服 他都不看你
Thank you for taking us in.
感x你我M
Even if you are not out to undermine our oppressors,
即便你不是槲除掉_R暴君的
friends of Zo are always welcome
我也要g迎_的朋友
because he has so few.
因樗]朋友
What about the Castel Sant Angelo that connects to the Vatican?
B接梵蒂的}天使堡呢?
If I can devise a way to reach the tower...
要是我可以O法接近塔...
Leo, listen. Just listen to me.
R昂 著 你我f
It's a prison.
那是Oz
Okay? Did you enjoy your time in the Bargello that much?
好? 你那N喜g待在巴格Oz?
You're homesick for iron bars?
你想念F诹?
These are the people who put me behind those bars, Zo.
把我PMF诟说恼是他 _
And they will pay for their folly.
他要榇烁冻龃r
- See you.  - Farewell.
- 再  - 再
Niccolo.
尼科洛
Your wife Lucrezia, she is a believer, is she not?
你的妻子R克蕾RI信教吧?
She is, Your Magnificence.
是的 w下
Well, is she unwell? I've not seen her of late.
她身w不好? 我最近]看到她
She's been caring for an aunt in Siena.
她去a耶{照看她的姑了
I'd hoped she'd be here by now but perhaps God has other plans.
我希望她能在@Y 不^或S上帝另有安排
Your excellency,
殿下
would it be impertinent of me to say you wear your ashes well?
我可以冒昧地f句 你看上去很虔\?
I like my women with a bit of cheek.
我喜g冒昧的女孩
You've gathered all the curfew ledgers as I asked?
我要的`禁名文愣颊业搅?
- I have, signor.  - Excellent.
- 找到了 先生  - 很好
Bring them to my quarters.
搬到我房g去
Oh, Francesco.
噢 弗朗切斯科
Buone Feste.
日快
Let us heal old wounds.
我把不愉快都忘吧
Yes, and put old feuds to death.
好的 忘之前的不快
We look forward to the union of our families.
我期望杉铱梢FY
Assuming we can work out the terms of the dowry.
我可以把嫁y的事妥
He jests.
他在_玩笑
I'm sure it will sort out.
我相信那不成}
Since you've extended the first laurel,
既然你首先表示友x
we'd like to host an engagement fete for the families
我意出Y榧易
at our country estate.
主k婚宴
A Lord's supper for Holy Saturday.
也是突罟前夕的}餐
This is good news, Francesco.
@太好了 弗朗切斯科
This is good for Florence and this is good for us all.
Ψ鹆__好 ξ大家都好
- Till Holy Saturday then.  - Indeed.
- 那就突罟前夜了  - 好的
Farewell.
保重
Well done.
做得好
Now all you have to do is break the news to Giuliano.
F在你只需把@消息告V朱利Z
Let's be clear on this, I get no choice in this matter.
首先f清楚 我在此r事上eox
None. Because you are my brother,
是的 因槟闶俏业艿
you get an explanation of why you have no choice.
@就是你eox竦脑因
Camilla Pazzi.
卡米拉・帕吉
You can't deny she is attractive.
你必承J她很迷人
If I needed a new mistress, I'd bed her myself.
如果我需要新情人 肯定睡了她
The Pazzis have other marriageable maidens without so much appeal.
帕吉家有其他的未婚少女 但就]@N漂亮了
Clarice was looking out for you.
克拉斯也是在P心你
You decided all this and you didn't even consult me?
你都不我一下就Q定了?
We thought that if the Pazzis turned us down,
我想著如果帕吉家拒^的
we wouldn't have to burden you with it.
我就不用麻┠懔
Easier to say from the seat of the bidder rather than the bidded upon.
你真是站著f不腰疼
Do you honestly believe this can work?
你真的X得@幽苄?
The Pazzis have been our foes since the days of our ancestor Averardo.
奈祖先阿S拉多_始 帕吉家族就是我的橙肆
Feuds like that don't just go away.
如此的宿仇是不化解的
This is precisely why marriage was invented!
所以人才l明了和H
To consolidate power and to settle feuds.
固萘 化解宿仇
Yeah. I always knew I'd pay for being me.
度 我一直清楚要樽约旱纳矸莞冻龃r
Lucrezia. What are you doing in Rome?
R克蕾RI 你在_R做什N?
Who says we're in Rome?
lf我在_R的?
How did I get here?
我是怎N到@旱?
I told you I loved you.
我告V你我勰
So I found a way.
所以我找到了方法
And don't think I didn't notice
而且e以槲]注意到
you haven't answered my question.
你]回答我的}
It is easier to resist at the beginning than it is at the end.
_始比Y束r更容易抵制
But then again, perhaps you're not capable of love.
但f回 或S你根本不懂
You stay silent even when I've given you my dearest possession.
我o你自己的珍r 你仍然保持沉默
Can't you tell from this what you mean to me?
你看不出砟ξ业囊饬x?
Can't you tell me what I need to hear?
你就不能跟我f我想的?
I...
我...
Without love, there is no point in living.
]有 活著有什N意思
Hey, hey! Rouse yourselves. Rouse yourselves.
嘿 嘿! 醒醒 醒醒
I've discovered a way into the Vatican.
我找到去梵蒂的路了
Bugger off. You're still drunk.
走_ 你醉著呢
What is the one place, the one entrance,
那]有守l的地方 那入口
where no guard can be found?
在哪呢?
It's in the water.
在水Y
The sewers were built on the principles of Vitruvius.
下水道是根S特威原理建造的
Designed to flow freely into the city,
可以穿整城市
including into the Vatican.
包括梵蒂
Look, look.
快看 快看
The air is delivered into the glass and it allows the flame to live.
空膺M到玻璃瓶Y火焰可以燃
Now I know you're besotted. You won't fit inside there.
你真是糊T了 你不M那玻璃瓶的
Of course not, but we can construct a device of similar properties.
然不行 但我可以造一相同性能的b置
Look at these sketches. Here. Here. Look.
看@些草D @ 在@ 看
Look.
快看
It's a diving dress.
@是套水服
It's modeled on the breathing of a water turtle.
是仿照水的呼吸原理u作的
Because the air goes in through this line,
空馔ㄟ^@lM去
and then it's exhaled into this forward pouch.
然後M到前面的袋子Y
Look. We need to gather some items and do it quickly.
著 我需要收集材料 幼饕快
We've only got a few days.
我只有滋rg了
- There.  - Pig's skin, glass...
- o你  - i皮 玻璃...
a fishing net...
OW...
- a boat?  - Yes, a boat.
- 有船?  - 是的 船
Right.
]e
This is the spot.
就是@地方
Okay, just continue operating the mechanism at a steady pace
好了 要保C@b置定地\行
until I reach my destination.
直到我到_目的地
Once I'm there, I'll plug the end of this line as signal to stop.
一旦我到了 我塞住@^作橥Ｖ沟男盘
Leo, are you sure of this contraption? We haven't tested it.
R昂 你_定@b置能行? 我]有^
There's no time if we're to remain undiscovered. It's trial by fire.
]有rg了 我不能被lF 就勇J火吧
Or water, in this case.
或者f水
Just keep pumping these bellows.
只管拉L箱吧
With any luck, it'll take just a few hours to get all the way inside.
幸\的 只要小r就可以M去了
What if you're wrong about where you'll emerge
要是你把浮出的地c弄e了
and you climb up into a brigade?
碰到大l兵怎Nk?
The plans of Vitruvius show where the drains lead.
S特威的D案@示了下水道的走向
Yes? Once I reach the reservoir,
Π? 一旦到_蓄水池
I just drill up into the Vatican flooring.
我到梵蒂的地面上
If I don't reappear by sundown,
如果我日落r]出F
make your way back to Florence without me.
你就为回佛__
- Sundown?  - Honestly? What could take so long?
- 日落?  - 不是吧? 怎N需要@N久?
Hey. Bell time.
嘿 打烊了
Bell.
打烊了
Another!
再硪槐!
Signor de Medici, we're about to ring the bell for the night.
美第奇先生 今晚打烊的rg到了
Then bring me a barrel I can roll home and drink all night.
那o我一桶酒 我搬回家通宵筹
I need all the liquid counseling I can get.
o我再多的戒酒建h也不檫^
Would you believe my brother pledged me to marry a woman from...
你能相信我哥哥逼我娶一女人...
All right, skirts.
好了 姑娘
Dragonetti's wolves will be here for a round-up soon.
德拉戈奈蒂的l很快就砹
It's time to find your beds.
回家了
You too,
您也是
your grace.
大人
And what if I called your bed my home for tonight?
要是我想在你床上^夜呢?
Sorry.
抱歉
Too much cider.
酒喝多了
Seems my cock doesn't know what's good for him.
看砦业睦隙不知道什N是好的
Luckily I do.
幸好我知道
Strange noise. Did you hear that?
真奇怪的音 你到了?
Zo, Zo.
_ 有人砹
Is it down there?
在@下面?
No, come on.
不是 走吧
Zo.
_ 快c
I boiled you some quinto quarto for your hangover.
我o你煮了醒酒
It works wonders.
很有效的
You're a saint.
你真是}女
I think we disproved that last night.
我想昨晚f明我不是了
Oh...
哦...
There's something you have to know.
有些事你必知道
I'm betrothed.
我已婚了
You mentioned it.
你f^了
A few times.
好状
I agreed to your advances precisely because you're spoken for.
我恰恰是因槟阌婚了才同意你的示鄣
If you were unattached and we became enamored with each other,
如果你]婚 我又勰缴狭吮舜
can you imagine what might happen?
你能想像l生什N?
A Medici marries a commoner.
美第奇家的人娶了平民
Would it be so bad?
有@N糟?
Lady Vanessa?
瓦妮莎小姐?
Your palace is a prison with better linens.
你的m殿不^是A的Oz
Every move is watched, every action judged.
一e一佣急槐O 被人u^足
My choices might be limited here,
我在此的x窕蛟S有限
but I answer to no-one but myself.
但我只需忠於自己
Why don't I sack it all and come and live with you on your side of things?
我何不放一切砗湍闵活在一起?
Without the Medici hand governing,
]有美第奇家族的治理
I'd still be living a lie in the convent.
我永h活在修道院的e言Y
It would have been a gentle lie,
但那是善意的e言
a lie lived among friends...
在朋友中的e言...
Oh.
哦
But if I marry Camilla Pazzi, that's a lie too.
但如果我娶了卡米拉・帕吉 那也是一e言
When you marry her, you neutralize that family of fiends.
你娶了她 你化干戈橛癫
And when ruling Florence gets to be too much,
y治佛__毫μ大r
you and I can still snatch a little freedom here and there.
你我仍然可以不r地偷g
You know this makes good sense.
@雍芎冒
Something else stops you.
有事你q豫
I blame the Pazzis for Becchi's death.
我X得是帕吉家族害死了奇
They set him up somehow.
是他陷害了他
Along with Rome and their spy.
c_R有他的g一起
Well, then, clear his name.
那就洗清他的罪名
And then the Pazzis will know just what sort of man lives among them.
之後帕吉就知道是什N拥娜松活在他中g了
Amen.
阿T
May I present Federico da Montefeltro,
允S我介BM德Y科・_・蒙泰M特_
the Duke of Urbino.
比Z公爵
- Federico.  - Your Eminence.
- M德Y科  - w下
Thank you for travelling so far, so quickly.
感x你不hf里 迅速泶
Anything for Your Holiness.
Sr候命
I am but a servant of God.
我只是上帝的W人
And yet you ally yourself
而你s合
with your godson Lorenzo de Medici against us.
你的教子洛佐・美第奇抗我
Do I? A surprise to my ears.
是? 真是奇了
- Hm.  - I see.
- 嗯  - 我懂了
So you deny meeting Lorenzo in your home
那你是否J在家和洛佐面
to negotiate an alliance against the Papal States?
商Y盟抗教皇y治了?
Please forgive my nephew.
原我的侄子
These rumors have angered him greatly.
那些{言他非常生
No apologies necessary.
不需道歉
If I'd heard similar, I'd react the same.
要是我 我也如此的
Or worse.
或者更糟
5,000 gold florins to fight for us against the Medicis.
槲抗美第奇家族 就p你五千金弗_林
Now, apologies are necessary.
F在 你必道歉了
You think Condottieri kill only for money?
你Jl蜍只是榱隋X⑷?
Some I kill for pleasure.
有些是榱啡
Federico, let's have you refreshed before we discuss our business.
M德Y科 在正事前先你t解情r
We shall reconvene after.
我稍後再聚
Signor?
先生?
Signor de Medici?
美第奇先生?
Who's there?
l啊?
Signor de Medici requested these lists.
美第奇先生索要了@些名
Dragonetti produced the index of symbols?
德拉戈奈蒂K於o你索引了?
I had to invade his office without his knowledge.
我得偷偷地M入他的k公室
I'll let you gentlemen get to work.
我不打_你工作了
Somehow I never got to my chores last night.
昨晚的s活]滞
- Signorina.  - Bye.
- 小姐  - 再
Tell me. Who's Libra?
告V我 天秤座代表l?
I'm sorry, Eccellenza.
抱歉 殿下
It's the symbol for Gentile Becchi.
@是金泰・奇的苏I
Libra, the scales of justice.
天秤座 正x的天平
If only we can deliver that to him.
能他知道@就好了
- Capricorn?  - Moses the physic.
- 摩羯座?  - 摩西t生
Understandable. Illness respects no curfew.
可以理解 疾病可]有宵禁
That leaves Gemini. Who is he?
那就剩下p子座了 他是l?
I don't think our conspirator is Gemini.
我不J殡p子座代表了叛徒
That's the symbol for, well...
@符是...
Lucrezia Donati?
R克蕾RI・多{蒂?
Forgive any indelicacy, but you surely know why she's out late at night.
冒犯之原 但您肯定知道她楹芜@N晚在外面
I do.
我_知道
And yet, the week we hired Da Vincis,
但是 我l蜻_芬奇的那周
- "Returning from Siena."  - Mm.
- "腻a耶{返回"  - 是的
I hear she's there now. She could have been easily visiting relatives.
我fF在她就在那 可能是在探望H戚
She could have just easily traveled to Rome
也可能是去了_R
and alerted them of our new war engineer.
警告他我有了新工程
It's impossible. She's a... woman.
不可能 她可是... 女人啊
Exactly.
正是
Her liaisons with my brother create an unquestionable alibi.
她和我哥哥的PS成了天衣op的托o
But we cannot ignore the possibility that Lucrezia is a spy.
但我不能排除R克蕾RI是g的可能性
Saddle the horses for Siena.
漶R去a耶{
We'll question her directly.
我面她
Gentlemen, gather round.
先生 集合
Bernardo Baroncelli.
@是博{多・巴隆切Y
Jacomo Bracciolini.
@是Z科莫・ 波拉萄Y尼
Condottiere Giovan Battista.
虮L掏吣帷ぐ偷偎顾
Renato Giustini.
@是雷{托・朱斯蒂尼
Father Bagnone.
巴尼W壬窀
Father Maffei.
R菲教父
Your Eminence, Cardinal Orsini.
尊敬的W西尼t衣大主教
Some may call us conspirators.
有人f我是叛\
I say no. Gentlemen,
我J椴 士
look upon each other as saviors of our great city.
在座的每一位都是我ゴ蟪鞘械木仁乐
Ahhh.
啊
And here's our final savior.
@位就是最後一位救世主
Gentlemen.
先生
- The front door was locked.  - Who dares?
- 前T被i上了  - l@N大?
Leonardo Da Vinci.
R昂{多・_・芬奇
The man you sought to have imprisoned and burned.
那你D囚禁K死的人
The Florentine virtuoso.
那佛__的大
You make quite an entrance.
你M淼姆绞胶吞e
To ensure a private audience.
要_保我不被人打_啊
The Secret Archive, if you please.
密室 路
As you wish.
如你所
I'm aware of the guards outside.
我知道外面有ol
Surely a Secret Archive
密室
has an attendant secret passageway.
然有一秘密通道
Then find one.
那就找出戆
This palace was designed by Nivolo Speziali, no?
@所教廷由尼瓦_・斯佩R里O的 Π?
And his structures are historically rife
他的建BL格在v史上很有名
with hidden doorways,
他喜g\用暗T
tunnels.
隧道
And judging by the direction of that breeze,
根微L的方向
I would say...
我J...
a passageway most likely lies behind this wall.
通道就在@堵後面
I have agreed to Lorenzo's cunning plan of a marriage,
我同洛佐^妙的姻
only because it will never happen.
因樗^Σ豢赡F
Accepting it obliges the Medicis to join us here on Holy Saturday.
美第奇家族答要在}L六(突罟前夕)^
Do we kill Lorenzo coming up the path
要在洛佐^淼穆飞邮
or have my men attack along his journey?
是我的人埋伏在途中?
Count Riario commands that we strike only when the brothers are together.
瑞阿里W伯爵命令 只有他兄弟在一起的r候 我才能邮
Lorenzo and Giuliano enjoy separate but equal sway
洛佐和朱利Z的喜好不同
over the loyalties of the people.
但臣民不是效忠於此便是效忠於彼
If they are not killed simultaneously,
如果他]同r死
then the survivor will reclaim power.
存者重新掌
Eliminate both brothers at once and we cripple their line.
一旦把他兄弟除去 我就能削弱他的萘
And as soon as they're dead,
只要他死了
Nazzareno Dragonetti, with his Officers of the Night, steps in.
{扎雷Z・德拉戈{迪就以他的值夜官身份 掌
Can we be so sure?
我能相信他?
This is the man who spent years doing the Medicis' bidding.
那可是一效忠美第奇家族多年的人啊
I must agree.
我也岩
What assurances do we have that your loyalty lies with our purpose?
那N 你又拿什N碜C明你的忠\呢?
My allegiance is to my family.
我效忠於我的家庭
And to Florence, my home.
效忠於弗洛_ 我的家l
And what of Lorenzo's wife?
那洛佐的妻子怎Nk呢?
My sister, Clarice.
我的妹妹克拉斯
As the Bible says,
如}所言
a woman leaves her home when she weds.
女人一Y婚就不再是娘家的人了
She's no longer truly your sister.
某N意x上 她已不是你妹妹了
However,
但是
you will be handsomely rewarded for the loss you endure,
等到最K你回到_R 你真正w俚牡胤降r候
as you finally return to Rome where you belong,
你的付出Q碡S厚的回
Vice Chancellor to the Holy Father.
}父的副司祭
As each of you will be rewarded.
在座每一位都@得S厚的蟪
Isn't this what we complain of in Lorenzo?
@不正是洛佐的做法?
That he is not a leader of a republic
他已然不再是帝的IЯ
but a tyrant dividing his spoils among his cronies?
而是一只及臣的暴君?
Are we just exchanging one family of nepotistic leaders for another?
我就不能改@N任人唯H的局面?
Basta!
巴斯塔!
Take a drink, brother, and calm down.
喝杯酒 兄弟 然後冷oc
Like any new leaders, we...
像其他新上任的Iб...
we promote those loyal to us.
忠於我的人能平步青
But Lorenzo is a weak, bankrupt traitor
但洛佐是一懦弱 F
hiding behind political privilege.
躲在政治特嗟谋幼o下的叛\
How is Florence a world power
如果W洲知道是@右人在y治我的帝
if Europe knows our republic is in such hands?
佛__能如何掌控世界?
The Pazzi name offers legitimacy and security
帕吉家族能蚶用他的Q易夥伴
with trade partners and neighboring armies.
和盟提供合法保o
The time to question your allegiance is...
z你忠\的r候...
well, it's long past.
哦 已^了很久了
That is how the Medicis will die.
美第奇兄弟@铀廊
Quickly.
D瞬之g
Stand with us or... not at all.
效忠於我 或者... 死
Viccolo della Manna.
S克洛・娜
The home of Lucrezia's aunt, Anna Donati.
安娜・多{蒂 R克蕾RI姑的家
Signora, are you Anna Donati?
女士 您是安娜・多{蒂?
We require your niece, Lucrezia.
我找你的外甥女R克蕾RI
Has she not returned home?
她]回家?
She was here, but she left for Florence days ago.
她之前在@Y 但滋烨熬由砘胤鹆__了
You understand we'll need to look around.
不好意思 我要M去看一下
Did she take the road to Poggibonsi
她走的是波吉邦西那l路
or through Chianti?
是基安蒂那?
Poggibonsi, of course. It's safer.
然是波吉邦西了 那l路安全些
If you hear from her, send word to me immediately in Florence.
如果你有她的消息 立即o佛__l信通知我
Of course.
然
Behold.
看啊
If it is treasure you seek,
如果@就是你要找的
this chamber contains more that you should ever require.
@g屋子可h超^了你期望的
It appears we awe even Da Vinci.
即使_芬奇也感到@奇了
I'm just astonished...
我只是震@於...
at what tyranny can steal.
一暴虐M的人能`取如此之多
Blood was the ransom paid for these artifacts.
@些精@的工品都是r血Q淼
Hypocrisy from a man who threatens my life.
碜砸威{我命的人的紊
Voiced by one who attempted to take mine.
碜砸D⑽业娜说穆音
Whose agent authored this denunciation...
是l的@封匿名信...
to have me burned.
害我差c被死的
But this is in a woman's hand.
@是一女人的PE
Could you truly believe I would employ a daughter of Eve as an agent?
y道你相信我l蚺人k事?
I seek a key.
我要找一把匙
The second needed to open the Vault of Heaven.
打_"天穹"的第二把匙
For this you would risk death?
榱诉@把匙你甘冒死?
Do not continue... with this ruse.
e^m... 玩你的把蛄
You aim only to delay me
你想拖延rg
until your absence is noticed by your guards.
直到你的ollF你的失
Your mind is restless.
你牟煌Ｖ顾伎
Yearning for that which most cannot comprehend.
探索著那些最y以理解的|西
God can end your longing.
上帝可以使你解
For He presents you the chance to explore
因 他⑺湍阋环荽蠖Y
all the mysteries of this chamber.
o你一C去解_@g屋子人有的i
If you would only agree to replace Cardinal Mercuri.
只要你答代替莫克Yt衣大主教
You would entice me to become keeper of the Secret Archives?
你在引T我做一密室的守o者?
Not keeper. Oh, no, no, no.
不 不 不是守o者
Its explorer.
是探索者
Come with me, Da Vinci.
跟我 _芬奇
Come with me...
跟我...
and then tell me you're not intrigued.
然後你就不f]有牧
So, what now, Signor?
w下 那F在怎Nk?
If she has nothing to hide, she'll take the road through Poggibonsi.
如果她]什N好[m的 她就x癫吉邦西@l路
But if she conspires against us,
但如果她背著我策什N
she'd find a way to ride alone through Chianti.
她就x褚人走基安蒂@l路
Which road do we take?
那我走哪l路?
We prepare for the worst and find ourselves relieved if we were wrong.
我做最牡拇蛩 即使推ye` 也不耽`什N
Through Chianti.
走基安蒂
- Cara mia, who were they?  - That was Lorenzo's brother.
- 卡拉 他是l?  - 洛佐的弟弟
Perhaps I've been away too long.
或S是我x_的太久了
Or perhaps your own business in Rome has gone bad.
或S是你在_R的事情牧
I'd hoped to spare you knowledge of these matters.
我希望你e管@些事
Can no-one in Florence help you? What about Lorenzo?
在佛__就]有一人肯湍? 洛佐呢?
He sentenced a man he's loved for decades to death,
洛佐把一忠心耿耿跟S他多年的人送上刑
on suspicion of something I have done.
因樗岩赡侨吮撑蚜怂
Well, is there no-one else?
那就]有e人了?
Yes.
有
There is another.
有一人
A man who could invent an escape where none exists.
有一可以{空找到出路的人
The skull of a dragon.
的^骨
It would serve as a unique addition to your study
@成槟阊芯可物
of creatures and their anatomy, yes?
和解剖工作的良C 不是?
Perhaps you'd care to examine this.
或S你想要看一下@
The Spear of Destiny.
命\之矛
A lance used to pierce the side of Christ
在基督被煸谑字架上的r候
while He hung on the cross.
它曾刺^他
Many believe that in one's hands...
很多人相信 此矛在手...
it can defeat any enemy.
天下o
It's extraordinary.
巧Z天工
But what of the key?
但匙呢?
This obsession with the Book Of Leaves.
P乎~之啊
The Turk blinds you with tricks and deceptions.
那土耳其人在玩弄你
The Sons of Mithras are an extinct order.
密特拉之子早就缃^了
Those who advance its name now,
那些借他名x的人
conceal their real agenda.
都想把真正身份[藏起
In your quest, you unknowingly act as an agent for the Ottoman Sultan.
哪愕男雄看 你在不知情的情r下橥炼其帝的K丹人做事
My quest is not in pursuit of anyone's purpose...
我不命於任何人...
except my own.
除了我自己
Ah.
啊
And here, you speak of your mother, I presume.
我猜F在 你代表你母Hf
A treasure truly worth fighting for.
@_是一件值得橹^Y的事情
And one only I can aid in reuniting you with.
而且只有我能你重新F聚
What do you know of my mother?
你知道我的母H?
Holy Father?
}父?
Holy Father!
}父!
An enemy has entered the Vatican.
有人入了梵蒂教廷
Montefeltro, sound the alarm.
蒙泰M特_ 拉警
Pledge your allegiance to Rome
效忠_R
and you shall have the entire resources of the Catholic Church at your disposal.
整天主教教的所有Y源都槟闼用
Its coffers, devisings,
X 物 人
even the ships of the Papal Armada to ferry you.
就是教廷也你的派遣
And the Book Of Leaves? What if I should uncover that on my search?
那~之呢? 如果我的研究需要用到@本呢?
So much the better.
那就更好了
It's far too precious to be left unguarded.
它太珍F了 o人守o我可不放心
There was a time when I distrusted its very existence.
有r候我都岩伤是否存在
Until my eyes fell upon this.
直到我H眼看到它
Which we recovered from Florence.
我姆鹆__@得淼鹄品
Oh!
噢!
It's unlike any language I've ever encountered.
@不是任何一N我所知道的Z言
That is far from its only mystery.
h不止Z言本身的魅力
The words...
@些字...
they seem to... change with every viewing?
它好像... 每看一次都改?
Never offering the same content twice.
同拥热 ]出F^第二次
Imagine solving this.
想像著解_@i
I had a dream not long after I saw this.
我到@|西不久之後就做了一
A powerful message sent from the heavens.
碜蕴焯玫烈的信息
It told me the Book Of Leaves
告V我~之
contains... secrets of the divine.
Y面有... 神的秘密
That its authors were the Nephilim
它的作者是"落者"
the offspring of Angels and the women of man.
神和人所生之子
Father!
}父!
I know now that the Book with its mysteries
我知道那本和它的秘密一定
must remain within the Church.
藏在教Y
- No matter the cost.  - Is it defense or burial that you intend as its fate?
- o代r如何  - 你打算用它硎刈o自己是埋葬自己?
The world needs secrets.
世界需要秘密
Powerful ideas can wreak havoc if unleashed before their time.
如果天C漏 天翻地覆
But a new beginning can start with you here now, if you choose.
但同r也是一湫碌拈_始 @⑷Q於你
Hold, Montefeltro.
住手 蒙泰M特_
So... we are allied.
那N... 我是同盟了
You press for my devotion
你迫我槟阕鍪
as only to place me here
囚禁我的自由
as another relic in this tomb that you've constructed.
如同你H手打造的墓Y的一件陪葬品
Take him.
抓起
Get him!
抓住他!
Go!
走!
Nico! Come back here, you spongy pignut.
尼科! 回 憨
Your master returns.
你的主人回砹
Nico!
尼科!
Leo.
R昂
Come here.
^
You are completely mad.
你肯定是了
Oh, fuck.
死
I can't believe you stuck it to that fuck Riario.
真y相信你耍了那瑞阿里W
I wish I could see his face when he figures it out.
我真想看看他知道真相之後的幼
Wishes come true.
粝氤烧媪
Through here.
在@
Where is Da Vinci?
_芬奇去哪了?
I'm the last person he tells.
只有我知道
- Really?  - Yeah.
- 是?  - 是
Then... then perhaps I'll entertain myself,
那N... 也S我等他的r候
while I wait.
可以自首芬幌
The Vatican choir could use a new castrato.
梵蒂教廷可以增加一割^的歌手
Fuck.
死
Move away.
W_
Yeaargh!
哈!
Aaargh!
啊!
Oh.
哦
God! Fuck! Aargh.
天啊! 死! 啊
Do you know who I am?
你知道我是l?
Young Nico.
小尼科
I... I see our first encounter left your hand shaking.
我... 我lF咱第一次相遇你的手一直抖
I'll steady it in your heart.
我刺M你心Y
Will you? If revenge is your aim,
你? 如果你想蟪
you must overcome your apprehension.
必僮约旱目
Now that we've established my propensity for directness,
好的 我也表_了自己的直率
I have a question for you.
我要你}
Where is my Maestro?
我的大在哪?
Have you ever tasted blood, Nico?
你L^血的味道 尼科?
It erm... possesses a peculiar saltiness.
嗯... 有一N奇怪的咸味
Don't bother, Nico. He doesn't know.
e麻┝ 尼科 他不知道
Wouldn't reveal anything even if he did.
他就算知道也b不知道
- Yes, he will.  - You're quite right, Nico.
-  是的  - 很 尼科
I will tell you all about the dozen Swiss mercenaries,
我可以o你vv在我v的r候
I dispatched to the Tiber,
我往台伯河派出的
who search for me as we speak.
一沓搜の业娜鹗l蜍
I'll reveal my plan when they arrive,
等他砹宋医o你vv我的
to have them peel away your skin one layer at a time.
他一拥匕涯愕钠下
Like this?
就@?
Aaargh!
啊!
You don't want to travel this road.
你不想@拥
If you wish to see him bleed, let it be my doing. Come on, stop it.
如果你想他流血 我邮 行了 可以了
No! He's mine to face. And he will answer my question.
不！我要抗他 他要回答我的}
Where is he?
他在哪?
I commend you on your resolve, boy.
我很欣p你的Q心 孩子
In another life, in other circumstances,
Q做e人 若非此景此景
I could have used someone like you.
我一定跟你一
Aaaarh!
啊!
It's the second key.
是第二把匙
Okay...
好吧...
That's a curious tune.
@曲{很熟悉
May I ask... where you know it from?
我能... 你哪W的?
It's of my own construction.
是我的曲子
I've heard the lullaby before.
我^@支u@曲
You are Lucrezia Donati's father.
你是R克蕾RI・多{蒂的父H
Aren't you?
Π?
Indeed... Signor Da Vinci.
是的... _芬奇w下
Have we met before?
我以前^?
No, but who else so bedevils Riario?
]有 不^能有l瑞阿里W如此苦滥?
This ring belongs to you, doesn't it?
@只戒指是你的 Π?
Once upon a time. It was taken.
曾是 被拿走了
May I ask how you acquired it?
我能你是如何得到的?
It was a gift... from your daughter.
是你女... 送o我的Y物
No, it is far more than a gift.
不 @可不HH是Y物
Do you love my daughter?
你畚遗?
Do you love my Lucrezia, Leonardo?
R昂{多 你郾R克蕾RI?
Ha.
呵
I must confess...
我必承J...
I'm not sure who your daughter is, Signor.
我不_定你女菏钦l w下
Her image has always been... shaded to me.
她的身影... ξ碚f如此h渺
Perhaps now I know why.
也SF在我知道了原因
You...
你...
You present...
你就是...
a key piece in unlocking her puzzle.
解_她i}的PI因素
She offers me your ring,
她送o我你的戒指
but keeps your imprison...
s留你在OzY...
She keeps your imprisonment a secret.
她δ惚槐O禁的事b字不提
She...
她...
extends me her love...
o了我她的...
but she continues with Lorenzo.
s仍然c洛佐mp
She despises Riario... but she's barely met him.
她缀]^瑞阿里W... s如此鄙
She hopes... to save you.
她想... 救你
To protect...
保o...
This is in a woman's hand.
@是女人的PE
How can you be so blind?
你槭颤N如此盲目?
She maneuvers for Rome.
她是受_R操v的
She feeds my secrets to Riario.
她把我的秘密告知了瑞阿里W
She... she poisons her fellow citizens.
她... 她毒害自己同城的人民
She sees me imprisoned and left to burn.
她看著我入z 等待火刑
And it's all to set you free.
一切都是榱司饶
Lucrezia acts at the behest of others' cruel manipulations.
R克蕾RI全都是按照e人酷的操v行拥
She loves me. Blame that on me if you will.
她畚 ⒋w罪於我
Not her.
而不是她
Harder!
用力!
Remove yourself from the shadows.
陌涤爸鞋F身
Let us face your daughter together.
我共同面δ愕呐
Lucrezia labors to secure your freedom why stay?
R克蕾RI努力要拯救你槭颤N不走?
I'm exactly where I need to be.
我就在自己在的地方
I don't understand.
我不明白
Go now, Leonardo.
走吧 R昂{多
Return to my daughter.
回到我女荷磉
Tell her of my love.
向她表_我的
And your own.
有你自己的
Don't brood, Nico. He's fine.
e著急 尼科 他]事
What you did earlier,
你才
coming to my aid, was very brave.
椭我的行 非常勇敢
So... thank you.
呃... xx
Then I should thank you as well.
那我也x你
Maestro! You had us worried.
大! 我很心你
Nico, at least.
至少尼科很心
I'm just glad to leave this hellhole.
我只是很高d能x_@Y了
I'm afraid... I'm afraid...
恐怕... 恐怕...
I'm afraid I can't.
不行
I've failed to retrieve the key and I'll stay until I acquire it.
我]拿到匙所以不能走
- Leo.  - What?
- R昂  - 怎N?
Steel yourself for a surprise.
有@喜o你 e太高d
How?
什N?
Credit this malt-worm.
因樗@酒鬼
I wanted to gut the prick, but he'd not have it.
我本硐氚堰@砘锎趟 可是他不
Huh.
呵
Artista... I see you escaped.
g家... 我看到你逃出砹
And I see a key...
而我看到了一把匙...
that you will be giving to me.
是你要o我的
You best kill me first.
你最好先⒘宋
I will follow you to the ends of the earth to retrieve what's mine.
不然就算追到天涯海角 我也要找回凫段易约旱|西
There may come a day...
或S有一天...
where I am forced to take your life, Girolamo.
我不得已而取你性命 捷洛拉莫
It's not today.
可不是今天
I've come into your home...
我淼搅四愕募@...
and I've taken the thing that you hold dearest.
拿走了你最珍鄣|西
I erm...
我...
I plan to return the favor soon...
很快蟠鹉愕...
and take the one most dearest to you.
Z走你最珍鄣娜
Maestro, shall we just leave him?
大 我就把他留在@?
To be haunted by your mistakes, Nico...
被自己^e魂不散得M@ 尼科...
that's a fate far worse than death.
是比死亡更悲K的命\
Don't touch her. She's unclean.
e碰她 她不乾Q
Weren't we told she'd be in disguise?
y道]人告V我她窝b?
We can't pass her by. We're stopping her.
我不能她^去 去r住她
Halt!
停!
Halt. Halt!
停下 停!
Stay where you are.
e
Immunda!
依慕_!
- Unveil yourself!  - I'm hideous.
- 露出!  - 我很可怕
It's a woman. Riario said she'd be disguised as a leper.
是女人 瑞阿里Wf^她窝b成麻L病人
Show your face or we do it for you.
自己露出聿蝗晃就邮至
Take off the mask.
摘掉面具
Look who has all her fingers.
看看她一手指都]掉
No!
不!
You're no leper, Signora.
你不是麻L病人 女士
Stand down! I've been given orders by Count Riario of Rome,
退下! 我奉_R瑞阿里W伯爵之命
to bring information for Lorenzo de Medici.
槁佐・美第奇餍
Signora, you seem to be a sunrise behind.
女士 看砟愕南息有c^r了
We're on our own orders from Rome.
我也是奉_R的命令
Lorenzo and his dolt of a brother are to be assassinated.
洛佐和他的弟弟被刺
Your services are ended. As is your life.
你的任战Y束了 生命也是
I've never killed anyone quite so pretty.
我]⑦^@N漂亮的人
This will be different.
@次可不一恿
He said to make it look like brigands. Don't do one clean hit.
他f了要做的像I⑷嗽截的F 不要一Ψ夂
No.
不
That's for fighting us.
抗我
No!
不!
But first, let's give her something to remember.
不^首先 咱她爽爽
Halt! Stand down!
住手! 退下!
This doesn't concern you. Ride on.
不P你的事 走_
I am Giuliano de Medici,
我是朱利Z・美第奇
brother to His Magnificence, Lorenzo of Florence.
佛__督洛佐w下的弟弟
I order you to stop!
我命令你停手!
Romans have no authority here.
_R在@Y]有嗬
They will soon enough.
很快就有了
And they want this deceptive little tart dead.
而且_R要@不可靠的小婊子死
How has she offended Rome?
她怎用胺噶肆_R?
She spied for Count Riario and now he's done with her.
她是瑞阿里W伯爵的g 不^F在已用了
What use is a slattern like this with the Pazzis about to seize control of Florence?
帕吉家族想要掌控佛__ 用得著@右D?
Aaargh!
啊!
Signor!
w下!
Bertino!
博蒂Z!
Aaargh!
啊!
All this for a spy like you!
都是拜你@g所n!
Bertino was a good man. But so was Becchi.
博蒂Z是好人 奇也是
Goodness means nothing to you.
你根本不知道好有何意x
The hand that brought him the hemlock was yours, wasn't it?
是你o他去了毒芹 Π?
What possesses you to betray Lorenzo?
是什N你背叛洛佐?
To betray us all?
背叛我大家?
You would never understand.
你永h不明白
Aaargh!
啊!
You are the cunt of an overworked whore.
你@j壑y填的浪
As my brother fucked you in the ass,
我哥哥操你的r候
did you smile, knowing you were doing the same to him?
你是不是因橹道也在У羲 所以才能笑得出?
Let's return to him and see how he feels about all this.
我要你回去他 看他有何感X
Will he opt to break you on the wheel,
他以y民
in the public square, for the edification of the masses?
把你在V龅哪据上 被y棍打死?
Or will his shame lead him to kill you privately?
是因羞愧而私下你死刑?
Slowly, over weeks of time.
慢慢地 v抵
- Urgh!  - Oh!
- 呃!  - 啊!
Aargh! Aargh!
啊! 啊!